so this is another auna talk it's just
simply called question and
answer um there's a few questions from
somebody I don't know who that is and
then a
answers so the qu question first
question is there are those periods when our
is there are those periods when our
heart or mind happen to be absorbed in
things and become blemished or darkened
but we are still aware of ourselves such
as when some form of greed hatred and
delusion comes up although we know that
these things are objectionable we are
unable to prevent them from
arising could it be said that even as we
are are aware of them this is providing
the basis for increased clinging and
attachment and maybe is putting us
further back to where we
started so I say that again could we say
could could it be said that even as we
are aware of them this is providing the
basis for increased clinging and
attachment what is there awareness of it
or the thing in itself being aware of it
that's providing basis for further
clinging yeah right maybe it's putting
us further back to where we started from
right but says well can you read again
the question from the start let me say
it first and then tell me what
says so
so the question begins there are those
periods when our minds happen to be
absorbed in things and become blemished
or darkened but we are still aware of
ourselves such as when some form of
greed hatred and delusion comes up
although we know that these things are
objectionable we are unable to prevent
them from arising yeah that's it that
was that's the wrong assumption there
trying to prevent these things from
arising which which means not seeing
where your responsibility is but
overdoing it trying to get rid of trying
to prevent things from manifesting in
the first place but that's not on you
that cannot be on you so the response
you and that's why they would get
confused then and um and end up
revolving around the objectionable
States because they're
overdoing the aspect of trying to get
rid of it and that's how you bind
yourself with it like a dog that runs
around the post trying to get away from
the post you try to tight to the post
tries to get away from the post ends up
being Tighter and Tighter closer to the
post so if that person were to recognize
that they can't it's not up to you to
prevent things from manifesting or not
that's not your responsibility and
that's not the problem either but
usually people believe oh there is greed
in my mind I must get rid of it but
that's not the problem the problem is
you acting out of the greed out of
aversion and that's on you so you have
to be able to not interfere with thing
that has manifested on its own and then
recognize that that you're not
responsible for that and that's not the
issue and that's not the greed in itself
that's the prospect of greed being
presented but it's you then choosing to
act by Body speech or mind delighting it
by with mental delighting in it
welcoming it that's you're doing so when
the Buddha says you shouldn't Delight in
greed aversion delusion means that you
don't Delight in what has presented
itself that doesn't mean I must get rid
of what has cuz that would mean that you
are in control that you are that you do
have a say as to what appears what
doesn't but the fact that if you were to
truly have a say these things wouldn't
have Arisen in the first place but they
do arise on their own and you have no
say yet you go around acting like you
have a say why cuz you don't know where
the problem is so you think the problem
is in
manifestation and not in the attitude
your attitude towards the manifestation
so that's where the restraint comes
first not to prevent things from arising
but to enable you to allow things to
arise without acting out of towards them
without acting out of it out of that
pressure of arising and the more
restrained you are means the less
interfering with things manifestation
you would be
doing anyway carry on anyway a answers
that says that's it one must keep
knowing them at that point that's that's
the method of practice knowing them in
the point of their arising yeah so the
then the question asks I mean that
simultaneously we are both aware of them
and repelled by them but lacking the
ability to resist them they just burst
forth so they come best forth unless you
act you choose to act out of them that's
what they don't see you push them
forward yeah the pressure might be yeah
sure but no no amount of the pressure
can sort of make a choice for you it's
always you who chooses to act out of the
pressure which means you can also choose
not to act which means you are the the
the the doorway through which the
pressure can enter because you are the
one who opens the door or doesn't MH not
knowing that then yeah you you it feels
like as if the action came automatically
out of the pressure because you haven't
practiced restraint sufficiently enough
properly enough so you haven't discerned
that line for which you're responsible
after which like you don't
cross he gives a
simile just go over it he says from then
on there will just be a rising and
passing way in this place the the same
same as waves striking the seash shore
when a wave comes in and finally reaches
the shoreline it just disintegrates and
vanishes a new wave comes and it happens
again the wave going the wave going no
further than the limits of the shoreline
in the same way nothing will be able to
go beyond the limits established by
one's own awareness that's it nothing
can enter through that door cuz you
realize nothing could have ever entered
it's you who was going out through the
door and being affected by things that
are outside so it was you who was
stepping from the shore into the water
that's being HD by the
waves that's exactly what I'm talking
about you start Discerning where your
respons abilities and then you don't
cross it so you realize the mind can
arise in all shapes and forms whatever
it wants whichever way it
wants that's not a problem that never
was a
problem you welcoming it entertaining it
trying to get rid of it that's what the
problem is so you stop doing that means
that which used to be uh basis for acts
of greed still arises but there is no
greed cuz greed comes from you doesn't
come from
things that which used to be basis for
ill will still
arises but there is no ill will now in
regard to it so the waves still continue
to come and go but you don't get wet
anymore because you don't go outside
where the waves are you recognize and
people start going outside or they carry
on going outside where you don't
recognize where the where the safety
from the wave is as well so you think I
must prevent waves from coming that's
the only way to remain dry mhm but it
isn't you just have to see the range of
the wave and allow it to basically
Express itself so to speak that's what I mean
itself so to speak that's what I mean
you have to recognize things in their
manifestation they have manifested on
its own the wave has come on its
own so it's you who goes there and tries
to push the C
back that's when you that's basically
that's what person's question implied
how do I how do I like deal with this
from arising so it doesn't arise because
for him automatically coming of the
waves means automatically me walking
into the water and getting wet he can't
see the difference between the two
things means flood means flood means wet
means soaked
drenched but if you were to recognize no
no no the wave can come as like tsunami
wave it still can't cross this line
unless I cross it that
way and that's what I mean that's where
sensory strain will enable you to start
Discerning that without sens restraint
yeah wave means I'm I'm in the water I
just swimming with it or trying to
trying to go against
it so actually the simul is quite
accurate the simul is quite good cuz
once you start Discerning that it's like
like finding that a single doorway
through which things come in because you
invite them in or that island that no
flood can overwhelm the island that no
flood can overwhelm or as the Buddha
gave the other one the the the town
that's rounded by the wall and there is
only one point of entry and exit and you
realize well if I want to keep track of
what's going on inside
I don't need to chase people who come in
and go after people they go out I just
need to stay at the
doorway the doorway of that the mindful
context in regard to feeling in regard
to Perceptions in regard to
intentions not the doorway of focusing
on the tip of your nose where you're not
aware of and that's basically like you
staring at the actual doorway and you
don't see who walks through the doorway
cuz you're staring at the woodwork of it
no you want to see okay whoever comes in
I know that it's in because there's no
other way of going out so whatever
manifests itself you know it manifested
to this extent and there is lust in the
mind in regard to it or there is non
lust in regard to it neither of those
things are still a problem the problem
is when you start entertaining the lust
and then welcoming it welcoming the
prospect of of what that last is
pointing at and that's how you start
acting out of the
desire but if you don't act out of
desire and ill will those things cannot
enter your mind even when you actually
act those things can't enter your mind
that's why freedom from those things is
possible in the first place but choice
is is not mine choice is not mine yeah
well see people you can eventually work
your way up whereby you see the actual
present Choice as not being able to be
owned by you but until you work your way
up in this gradual manner all you're
going to be doing is denying the choice
after you made it and that's a form of
determinism like you made a choice but
then you say well there's no self so
this Choice couldn't have been
mine well it was yours when you were
making it how do you know that it was
rooted in greed or aversion or
distraction and delusion and whenever
there is any of these three there is the
conceit that is sense of I am which
means it is your
choice so the the better way to go about
it not to kind of deny it in hindsight
but actually take it as a blanket rule
that the choice is always yours so
through that sense of responsib ility
for the slightest choice you make you
can then eventually overcome the
ownership of the choice and
responsibility with it not remove the
responsibility for the choice so in
order to in order to remove the
ownership of responsibility you have to
stop denying
responsibility and people deny
responsibility when they say well choice
is not mine nothing is
mine or people try to deny
responsibility when they try to prevent
things there were basis for the choices
like the question in
applied so as ad CH pointed out you you
have to
stop well you have to stop engaging with
things on that level but start
Discerning where you're doing is and
they stop doing it and that's that safe
sh you find that it's inaccessible to
these waves so these waves remain right
in front of you coming your way full
force but now you have confidence that
they can't cross cuz you know that they
can't cross because you stayed with it long
cross because you stayed with it long
enough and you saw that they can't cross
if you haven't stayed with it long
enough well you still doubt whether they
can cross or not which means you are
affected by
it like you you don't feel safe if you
doubt your safety you can't say you're
safe so the only way to stop doubting
your safety is to to discern what that
safety is in regard to these things that
are assailing
you but the natural reaction is I must
prevent these things from assailing me
in the first place that's the true
safety it isn't I Must Destroy them I
Must Destroy them I must I must remove
them rather than get to safety exactly
rather than actually hold on I can't be
fighting the Sea and the waves and the
elements all I can do is find a place
where those elements can't basically
can't set the foot
in and that's when the B is that
negative it's the unmanifested I'm
born and also you don't have to maintain
that of course not impossible to
maintain it impossible cuz maintenance is on the
it impossible cuz maintenance is on the
level of intention choice and this is
safe in regard to remember it no you
discern it in regard to the threat
that's why it requires no maintenance
because any
manifestation is a
threat which
means safety is in regard to any threat
which means it's in regard to any
manifestation so it's the independent
manifestation of thing which is not your doing that
of thing which is not your doing that
maintains your sense of safety which is
equally not your doing that's why our
hardship is
effortless once you develop it so you
only need manifestation you only need to
work initially to stop obscuring the
true nature of manifestations that it
cannot be owned because of that it's
impermanent that that it's
unsatisfactory because he doesn't have
that um sense of pleasure connected with
um sense of pleasure connected with
Mastery over things
and because of that it cannot be yours
hence it's not self but always then that
manifestation Discerning a
thing it uh reveals all the time that
safe Zone yes and that's the thing once
you fully understood it you don't have
to keep Discerning it yeah the only like
an AR saaka needs to keep Discerning it
because still because he still has
residues of habits of ignorance and lust
and so on so he has to keep going
against that grain until it's fully
purified and then there is nothing with
the grain
anymore I'm just saying this so people
don't devel not you like like Aran is
just constantly this is a manifestation
this is a man no whatever you're aware
of has been manifested to that extent
you're fully aware of it already and to
that extent you're fully free from it
already cuz there was nothing to affect
you in the first place that's thing well
and Aran then would you aware of that uh
it reveals the island yes yeah exactly
the island is revealed by the waves y
yeah so all you need the island is
outlined yeah by the Sea yeah yeah so
yeah that's why the The Unborn like if
the sea is born niana is The Unborn the
unmanifested so from whatever it's
manifested nibana is outlined by being
the opposite of that
undefined undesignated this is the
extent of undetermined
yeah and by recognizing that you can't
unrecognized it or go exactly yeah you
can't go back that way and pretend you
haven't recognize that you haven't
recognize the extent of manifestation
yes yeah because that is the true nature
of
manifestations they cannot be owned they
cannot be
pleasurable that's why you cannot be
your own
that is the true nature and that's why
Liberation from the ownership the sense of self and
from the ownership the sense of self and
the dependence on Pleasure is possible
because you actually get to discern and
then these things become inconceivable
if those things were not
truly Beyond ownership
unpleasant not your sense of self they
can be maintained in regard to it if
they were not truly like that you
wouldn't be able to free yourself from
it the sense of self would be the master
and owner of the experience but that
means there wouldn't be any problems of
suffering but the fact that there is a
problem of suffering means the sense of
ownership is incompatible with that
that's why human existence is a
discrepancy between how things actually
are and how you acting them to be which
is why you're responsible for their being
being
discrepancy to discrepancy any degree of
discrepancy determines the the degree
the degree of liability towards the
dukka there's no discrepancy no base for du
there's no discrepancy no base for du
that's that's in the scene there is just
the scene a is just a there's no
discrepancy there now the people
sometimes get a sense of it but then
they they look for the discrepancy at
the wrong place they look at the
discrepancy in the A and they try to
resolve a of discrepancy the scene must
be resolved of the lust in the verion
delusion of the discrepancy of it but no
lust in the version delusion is not in
the scene
it's in your attitude towards it that's
why you remove that kind of attitude you
undo it you extinguish it and um then
what you have is in the scene there's
just the scene in the her there's just
the her smell taste touch same thought
her smell taste touch same thought
thought but what person's question
implied is oh there is a scene of greed
aversion delusion how do I prevent it
from being
seen so he did he didn't see he doesn't
see that the issue was in his attitude
to was the scene not the scene so his
question of trying to deal with the
scene prevent
it make it not make it
unmanifest imply the wrong view of him
looking at the solution at the wrong
place